<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lying spirit in the mouth of the false prophet made made manifest, who seeks to pervert the right way of the Lord, and openth his mouth against the lord of life, and denies his light within, as appeareth in a book, entituled, The doctrine of the light within ... set forth by ... Henock Hovvet ... Some things therein being here answered in the light of the Lord ... Declared in the movings of the Lord for the truths sake, and that all deceit might be made manifest. / By one who is a lover of all those who love truth in the inward part. W. S.</title>
            <author>Smith, William, d. 1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05898</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184394</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47012656</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47012656</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174621</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05898)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2693:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lying spirit in the mouth of the false prophet made made manifest, who seeks to pervert the right way of the Lord, and openth his mouth against the lord of life, and denies his light within, as appeareth in a book, entituled, The doctrine of the light within ... set forth by ... Henock Hovvet ... Some things therein being here answered in the light of the Lord ... Declared in the movings of the Lord for the truths sake, and that all deceit might be made manifest. / By one who is a lover of all those who love truth in the inward part. W. S.</title>
                  <author>Smith, William, d. 1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Smith by Wing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Howet, Enoch. --  The doctrine of the light within.</term>
               <term>Inner Light --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174621:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LYING SPIRIT In the Mouth of the Falſe Prophet Made manifeſt, Who ſeeks to pervert the right way of the LORD, and openeth his mouth againſt the Lord of Life, and denies his Light within, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in a Book, Entituled, <hi>The Doctrine of the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the Natural Man, leading to eternal life, examined by Scripture-Light:</hi> Set forth by <hi>H. H.</hi> which is owned by <hi>HENOCH HOVVEY,</hi> called a <hi>BAPTIST</hi> in <hi>Lincolne,</hi> for whom it is printed, and by him diſperſed abroad.</p>
            <p>Some things therein being here anſwered in the Light of the LORD.</p>
            <p>With the Spirits Teſtimony to the true Light which every man that cometh into the world is enlightened withall, leading to eternal life, which hath unity with that Light and Spirit that gave forth the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <p>Declared in the movings of the Lord for the <hi>Truths</hi> ſake, and that all deceit might be made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now will I ariſe ſaith the Lord; now will I be exalted in the earth: Who ſhall ſet Briars and Thorns before the Lord in Battel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By one who is a lover of all thoſe who love truth in the inward part. W. S.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:174621:2"/>
            <head>The Lying ſpirit in the mouth of the falſe Prophet made manifeſt &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IN the beginning was all things created very good, in the wiſdom of God, and he took pleaſure in the works of his hands, and man was made Lord over them all, ſtanding in communion with the life in God; he had au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to govern the Creation in the wiſdom of God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the ſubtiltie of the Serpent overcame him, and prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over him, to turn his mind from the wiſdom and life of God, into the earth, to feed upon that which the Lord had forbidden, where he entred into the tranſgreſſion, and fell from the wiſdom and life from which he received power and authority to govern and rule, and ſo the curſe came over him, having loſt his innocency, being ſubject to the Serpents ſubtilty, which he yeilded himſelf unto, to be guided by, and ſo was driven out from his place of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency into the earth, to eat his bread in ſorrow all the dayes of his life. <hi>He that can read this, let him;</hi> For that ſubtile Serpent which led into the tranſgreſſion, leadeth ſtill in the tranſgreſſion all that yeild themſelves to his enticements, and are taken Captives by him at his will, and ſo are led by him to oppoſe that in which Gods love is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, to break his head, and to recover out of his ſnares: This being the great deſign of that roaring Lyon, to keep people in that which he hath led them into, and from that, which is to recover them from under his dominion; and this is that which was, and is an enemy to the righteous ſeed of God in all its appearances, through ages and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations unto this day, as is manifeſt in this generation of wicked and ungodly men, who in the envious ſpirit, ſets their faces to do miſchiefe, as <hi>Henoch Howet</hi> hath done, as his own words do manifeſt, who ſaith, <hi>he having had much to do with a generation of men that held forth another doctrine of converting, or another means of convincing of men in their naturall condition, then ever Chriſt or his Apoſtles did,</hi> and to prove this by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:174621:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>light, as he calleth it, he names 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.23. but here he is not in the light of the Scripture, (his own lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) for there is not ſuch a verſe as he hath named; and ſo he is here ſhut up, and let his mouth be for ever ſtopped in his ignorance, and blindneſs, who is charging a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men with holding forth ſome ſtrange doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and hath no teſtimony to what he ſaith; and yet he tells us he is a labourer in a good Vineyard, and that he knowes the enemy now rageth more by deluſions, then by open perſecutions; theſe being the dayes (in which if it were poſſible) to deceive the very Elect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. John</hi> ſaw many deceivers entred into the World in his time, which was thoſe that Chriſt Jeſus ſaid ſhould come to deceive the very Elect, if it were poſſible; and haſt thou been a profeſſor ſo many years, and haſt not ſeen them before theſe dayes? If thou hadſt not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that by which all deceivers are made manifeſt, and in which <hi>John</hi> ſaw them, thou mighteſt have ſeen them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years ago, and thy ſelf to be one of them, who ſpeakes a viſion of thy own brain, and not from the mouth of the Lord; and this is the doctrine which is contrary to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the enemy which now rageth both by deluſions, and open perſecution; for the ſpirit of deluſion never ceaſed from perſecution againſt all who bear forth a living teſtimony to the Goſpel and the power of it, but was alwayes an enemy to it, and laboured againſt it, as thou doſt, though thy labour be to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Then thou ſayeſt, thou haſt taken it upon thee as thy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to forewarn all men of that doctrine that teacheth men to look to the light within them for directions from their naturall condition all along, untill they come to that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate they call their perfection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is manifeſt from thy own mouth, that thy work was not wrought in God, nor thy duty in obedience to his movings, but taken upon thee in thy own will, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in thy own wiſdom, which is contrary to all that are ſent of God, &amp; labours in his Vineyard, who do not take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them any thing in their own wills, and call it their duty,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174621:3"/>but waits on the Lord, to be obedient to his movings, to receive from him what is their duty to perform unto him; ſo the Lord gives forth his word, and it is declared in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; but that which thou haſt taken upon thee at thy own will and pleaſure is all denyed, not being received from the mouth of the Lord; for thou who denyes the light within, and art forewarning people for looking to it, thou denies the Scriptures, and the ſpirits teſtimony therein, and thereunto; for <hi>David</hi> bare forth his teſtimony in the ſpirit of the Lord, <hi>That the light of Chriſt enlightned the world, and in his light they ſaw light.</hi> John <hi>teſtified that Chriſt was the true light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world. Chriſt ſaid he was the light of the world;</hi> and if this thou wilt owne, which thou ſayeſt thou art examining by, then ſhew who they are, and what ſort of people that Chriſt doth not enlighten, and whether he doth enlighten people with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or without them, and where is his light to be looked for, and walked in, and prove thy ſelf a labourer in Gods Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard; for all that were ſent of God, and laboured for him, exhorted all people unto the ends of the earth, to look un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt and be ſaved, and to turn from the darkneſs to the light; therefore repent and be converted, that thy ſins may be blotted out, thou who art in the Antichriſtian ſtate.</p>
            <p>Then thou ſayeſt, thou wilt endeavor to ſhew what the enemy (which thou ſayeſt is the light within) drawes peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to, which is, to take counſel at a corrupt heart; and ſaith, It is evident, if they look to that which they call the light within, two things being in communion, a diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent natural man, they are like to ſee nothing but ayrie notions, with ſpirituall working powers to delude within them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Haſt thou not made it evident, that the ſpirit of God liveth not in thee, and that thy body is not the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Holy Ghoſt, who knows nothing within thee to take counſel at, but a corrupt heart? Haſt thou been ſo long looked at to be a teacher of others, and now brought to confeſs, that man hath nothing to look at within him but a corrupt heart? Haſt thou then miniſtered from any
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174621:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>other principle, then from a corrupt heart? For ſhame give over deceiving people, and tell them plainly what it is thou takes counſell at, for ſome have ſeen thee, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from thee, becauſe a corrupt heart is thy counſellor, which leads thee into all confuſion; for thou here talks of a diſobedient natural man, and that he cannot ſee himſelf otherwiſe, if he look to the light within, and yet thou talks of obedience to Chriſts commands and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in another place; What is thy obedience performed in to Chriſts commands and ordinances, ſeeing thou ſayeſt that man is naturally diſobedient, and his heart corrupted, and nothing elſe to be looked at within him? Then hath not the Prince of the power of the Aire dominion over thee who ruleth in all the children of diſobedience? Conſider thy own words, and ſee if there be any thing in them beſides Airie notions.</p>
            <p>Then thou ſayeſt, But if they will ſay, they have no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Devill, or Prince of the Aire, then thou ſayeſt his deſign muſt needs be to bring them to conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a heart that is deceitful and deſperately wicked; and being deceitful, it will offer darkneſs for light, and ſo una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably put them in danger of being deceived.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thou haſt unvailed thy ſelf to all the children of light, who reads thee, &amp; ſees what thou art conſulting with, who denies the light and hates to be reformed by it, and deſpiſeſt the counſell of it, though it ſtand a faithful wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in thy conſcience to reprove thee of all thy ungodly deeds, which in the darkneſs is brought forth by thee, from thy wicked and deceitful heart which thou art conſulting with, being alienated from the life in God, thy fooliſh heart being blinded by the Prince of darkneſs, who hath dominion over thee; receive thy own words which thou haſt layd down, and then conſider what that is which makes the heart manifeſt, by which thou comes to ſee the heart to be corrupted, and the deſperate wickedneſs of it, and the danger of conſulting with it, and what it offers in that ſtate; ſubmit to that of God in thee, and own plainneſs of ſpeech, and thou canſt not deny but it is the light that makes all things manifeſt; for whatſoever doth make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174621:4"/>is light, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.13. ſo the heart being within people, the light which makes it manifeſt is there alſo, and ſearcheth the heart thorow all the corruption &amp; deceit of it; for all things are naked and bare before it; and this is ſo plain that all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may know that there is that in them which ſtands a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt all the deceit of their own hearts, and never doth conſent to ſin, but reproveth for it in the conſcience of every man, which is the light that Chriſt Jeſus doth enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten every man withall; therefore be not ſtiff-necked and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, but turn to the Lord God of Life and Power, and wait in the light which he hath enlightened thee withall, that thou may come to the knowledge of the glory of God and to feel his living Power mortifying ſin in thee, and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a clean heart within thee, before thou talk of obedience to Chriſts Commands, and the Apoſtles practice; for until thou obey the reproof of the light of Chriſt within, and turn at the reproof of it, to be guided by it, thou knoweſt not the firſt Principle of the pure Religion, though thou haſt made a profeſſion many years, nor haſt not ſet one foot into the way of Chriſt, though thou imagine a long travel in it, &amp; that thou art come to the end of it. So ſome of thy folly is here fully anſwered in few words and plainneſs, therefore ſilence fleſh, and contend no longer againſt that in which the love of God is made manifeſt to ſinners; and this I am made to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie in the power of the Lord for the ſeeds ſake; and he that can receive it, let him.</p>
            <p>Then thou ſaiſt, <hi>If they would yet excuſe themſelves, and ſay they do not take counſel at their own heart,</hi> then thou ſaiſt <hi>it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be evaded; but if they look to the light within for counſel, they muſt needs look to their own ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If thou wert not altogether in darkneſs, thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt here ſee thy confuſion, who art endeavouring to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn people, and knows not of what, neither can ſhew di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly what it is, but ſaiſt, <hi>If it be not a corrupt heart, then it is a deceived heart; and if not a deceived heart, then it is their own ſoul:</hi> How blindly art thou led from all light and truth! for if thou wert guided by the light of Chriſt, thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt have ſhewed in what a corrupt heart, and a deceitful heart differs, (if any difference be) and what the ſoul is,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174621:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>and in what part of man it is placed; for if thou knoweſt not this, then art thou wholly ignorant of all that which thou haſt been charging a generation of men withall; and all thy imaginations is denied, and thy confuſion and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders is returned again unto thee, as dung upon thy face.</p>
            <p>Then thou ſaiſt, <hi>To look to the light within, leads men to look at a Judgment here in this life, and ſo takes off mans expectati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n from eternal Judgement; and this</hi> (thou ſaiſt) <hi>gives licence for luſt to rule, and is an invitation for the world to lye ſtill in wickedneſs, and for the Epicure to ſing a delightful ſong to his ſoul, Soul, take thine eaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Saints witneſſed the Lord come near to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and every tranſgreſſion and diſobedience to receive a juſt recompence of reward; Doth not the Scripture ſtand a witneſs againſt thee? Did not <hi>David</hi> witneſs the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord to be true? and <hi>Moſes</hi> witneſſed all his ways to be judgement; and was not this known by them in this life, which brought them to fear the Lord, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from evil, and to ſtand in awe, and not to ſin? And doth this deny eternal Judgement? or give liberty for luſt or wickedneſs to rule? Or brings it not thoſe to ceaſe from the evil, whom the righteous Judgements of God takes hold upon? Therefore wo be unto all the Epicures who put the Judgement of the Lord afar off, and ſit down at eaſe in the fleſh, and makes their belly their god, minding earthly things, devouring Gods Creation to ſatisfie a luſtful appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, and ſo treaſuring up Wrath againſt the day of Wrath, and revelation of the righteous Judgement of God, who will render to every man according to his deeds, when the Workers of iniquity will not be known by him, but muſt all depart from him into the everlaſting fire, there to abide un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the eternal Judgement: Therefore I ſay unto thee, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and ſink down under the Judgement in this life, that all ſin and tranſgreſſion may be judged out of thy heart by the light and power of Chriſt, that eternal Judgement be not thy portion.</p>
            <p>Then thou ſayeſt, <hi>That to look al the light within carries a deceived people for a ſelf-loving heart, and to an imagination of perfection, and that their mouths are full of curſing and bitterneſs,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174621:5"/>and proud; and that their tongues proves them perverſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And here thou ſpeaks as if thou wert not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled, but as if thy tongue were thy own, and there was no Lord to be over it: But that which thou ſlanders the truth with, is denyed, (that is to ſay) That any who are guided by Chriſt the Light of the World, do bring forth any of theſe things which thou falſly accuſes them of, but thou art ſeen and read in that which is eternal, to ſlander the truth with that which hath Dominion over thee; yet is the Truth pure, and all thy dirt cannot ſtain it, and all who live in it have a ſure defence and a refuge from this ſtormy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt which the Devil hath raiſed up, even to ſhake the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the righteous; but it is a Rock higher then all, and above all, which the righteous are ſet upon, and there ſtand in ſafety; therefore either prove thy words, that ſuch fruits are brought forth by thoſe who look to the light within, and are guided by it, or elſe own thy confuſion, and in it thy ſhame.</p>
            <p>Then thou brings thy Reaſons why men are carryed head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to theſe deluſions, and mixeth the Scripture with thy reaſon, ſaying, <hi>It is evident from the Apoſtles Doctrine to the Corinthians,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. <hi>evidently ſhewing the cauſe to be Satans transforming himſelf into an Angel of Light,</hi> and ſayes, <hi>The word</hi> Transforming <hi>imports the carrying of himſelf through all forms as an angel or meſſenger of light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Apoſtles Words I own, and they ſhall ſtand a Witneſs againſt thee who denies the light by which he was guided, and ſo art gathering his words into thy Reaſon, but cannot thereby come into the life; and ſo thou reſts in the form, (out of the power) where Satan is transforming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as from thy own words, who ſaith he carries himſelf through all forms, then how canſt thou exclude him from thine? Therefore I ſay unto thee, and all who abide in forms with thee, Come out from him, for I deny both him and thy forms, that ſo it is plain from thy own mouth, that thou reſts in that into which Satan can transform himſelf, having the likeneſs, but is not the ſubſtance; and theſe are his Miniſters who are thus transformed by his deceitful working, as Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, though they be falſe Apoſtles,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174621:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>deceitful Workers, transforming themſelves as the Apoſtles of Chriſt; if thou haſt an ear open, thou mayeſt hear if theſe be not they who are labouring to uphold viſible things, as thou haſt done in thy Book, crying, The Ordinances of Chriſt, the practiſe of the Apoſtles, theſe are to be walked in, and ſo the imitation is taken up, and the viſible thing is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, as the Apoſtles of Chriſt, but the light, life, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God is denyed, in which they enjoyed the ſubſtance, which was ſweet to their taſte, who felt that the Lord was good; and this was not a thing viſible without them, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed within them, which was the Bread of Life, and Water of Life, into which Satan cannot transform himſelf; and this I own, and in my meaſure witneſs to be ordained of God from the beginning, who ſatisfieth the hungry with the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Houſe, and refreſheth the thirſty with the Rivers of his good pleaſure; and this thou art a ſtranger to, who denies Chriſt the light of the World, who is the Fountain where living Mercies are witneſſed: And ſo thou erres, not knowing the Scripture nor the power of God, though thou haſt made a long profeſſion of them, and can ſpeak much of them, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> could do, and as the Devil can do; yet whileſt thou denies that by which they were given forth, they are as Weapons formed againſt thee.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Reaſon (thou ſayeſt) <hi>is Natures darkneſs; for</hi> (thou ſayeſt) <hi>if the Epheſians were ſometimes darkneſs, then in that ſtate they had nothing but darkneſs [ſuppoſed Light] to look unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> All who are in the light, ſees thy darkneſs, vvho knows not Chriſt from Natures darkneſs, and calls him a <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Light;</hi> for Chriſt was in the <hi>Epheſians</hi> in that ſtate of darkneſs, though by them unregarded, as he is by thee; Wherefore he ſaith, <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee light;</hi> by the reproof of the light were they awakened, and did ariſe from their dead ſtate of darkneſs, and were made light in the Lord. And here was ſomething to be looked unto beſides the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kneſs, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved them in the darkneſs, as it doth thee and all the World, who refuſe to be guided by it, and rejects Gods viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; therefore thou art darkneſs, and abides in darkneſs,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174621:6"/>and knoweſt not whither thou goeſt, becauſe that darkneſs hath blinded thy mind.</p>
            <p>Then thou ſayeſt, <hi>Having ſhewed what this deluſion is a means to draw people to,</hi> thou wilt <hi>now ſhew what it is a means to draw them from.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this thy Wiſdom lays down in many particulars; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Firſt, it keeps us from ſeeking a City that hath foundations, the Doctrine of the Apostles &amp; Prophets, and that theſe people have a Chriſt they account more ſpiritual then the Carpenters Son, and that they will not have that man to reign over them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The City is witneſſed, into which no unclean thing can enter, but muſt abide without amongſt the Dogs and Sorcerers; and the Doctrine of the Apoſtles and Prophets is owned and enjoyed, and Chriſt is received who is King of Saints; but all thy inventions and imaginations is denyed, who knows Chriſt no otherwiſe then as the Carpenters Son, and ſo would have him to reign; if this be thy Faith, then prove by plain Scripture that Jeſus Chriſt is the Carpenters Son, or that his Dominion is exerciſed in that nature, elſe own deluſion to be upon thee, and thy ſpirit to be a ſpirit of error.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt made ſuch a mixture of thy own inventions with the Scriptures, that it is hard to draw the Wine from the Lees, for thou haſt altogether ſet Chriſt in oppoſition to the Light within, which the Saints never did; and yet thou ſayeſt, <hi>They that look to Chriſt, and are enlightened, their faces ſhall not be aſhamed:</hi> So here thou haſt confeſt none can be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened but ſuch who look to Chriſt, and thou haſt owned Chriſt to be the light which doth enlighten, therefore now it is laid upon thee, either to confeſs, or deny in plainneſs, Whether Chriſt doth enlighten people within, yea, or nay? if yea, then he is the light within which people are to look unto, and be ſaved, which thou art fore-warning people from as a dangerous deluſion. If nay, then it is laid upon thee to prove by plain Scripture where he is, how he doth enlighten, and how people may come to him, and receive him, and be baptized into him, and put him on, and be led by him; ſo the Work will be ſhort, and many Words needs not be multiplyed to manifeſt truth, for it ſtands not in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174621:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>word, but in power, though much thou haſt laid together in thy Book, as if truth did conſiſt or ſtand in many inventions; I am moved of the Lord to tell thee and all people, That the Lord is riſen to overturn all the inventions and imaginations of man, and all falſe wayes and worſhips, which are not in ſpirit and truth, and they ſhall fall and come to nought, though never ſo ſtrongly contended for; but that which is of God ſhall ſtand.</p>
            <p>Thy other particulars I ſhall here lay down, as in thy Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom thou haſt drawn them forth.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Thou ſaidſt <hi>the Light within, draws people from Chriſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in converſion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>From confirming in aſſurance, and working of us up to follow on to know the Lord by ſeveral viſitations.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>From the Doctrine of the Apoſtles and Prophets.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>From the blood of the Covenant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>From the experience of the creating Word.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>From waiting for commands of Gods loving kindneſſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And then thou concludes, <hi>That watching in the light within to bring us to perfection, will be a vain watch.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſhall here wait for thy Anſwer to be publiſhed, as to what is laid upon thee, for I have born my Teſtimony in the ſpirit of the Lord, againſt all that which thou ſayeſt the Light within leads people to; ſo in general I do deny that it leadeth any, or draws them from any one of theſe particulars which thou haſt laid down; for I am made to ſtand a Witneſs againſt thee in the power of the Lord, knowing that Chriſt Jeſus the Light of the World, who lighteth every one that cometh into the World, doth lead all that are guided by him, from all that which thou ſayeſt the Light within leads people to, and unto that which thou ſayeſt it draws people from, that ſo thou art calling the light darkneſs, and darkneſs light: And for what thou haſt ſaid in thy conſiderations upon <hi>Baxters</hi> Papers which thou ſaidſt was againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> thou haſt there conſidered nothing but what is carnal and viſible, ſaying your Water is in Fountains and Rivers viſible, and that the natural Tongue of the godly can ſhew the Way of Life to the natural ear and eye, and ſo to the underſtanding of the natural man; and much more ſuch like as this thou haſt conſidered of, which are all to periſh, as all other
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174621:7"/>viſible things muſt; and ſo thy hope will periſh with them, who knows not a life above them; but thoſe whom thou haſt ſet thy ſelf againſt, knows their life to be in that which is eternal, and will abide for ever, and are made to deny all thy viſible and carnal things, as rudiments of the World; and this I have alſo obſerved in thy Conſiderations, <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> made friends.</p>
            <p>I am moved of the Lord to tell thee, That whoſoever wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth in that Light which thou ſayeſt will be a vain watch, they ſhall be defended from the Enemies Power, for there doth the Lord preſerve his people, and keep them from the Heathens rage, though thou haſt bent thy bow, and ſhot thy Arrows at the upright in heart, they ſhall return again upon thee, for no harm ſhall come nigh the dwelling-place of the Saints of the moſt High; for who dwel in the Light are compaſſed about with mercies, and there are made to ſing ſongs of Deliverance; ſo thou art now to anſwer to what is laid upon thee, and expected from thee, that is, To confeſs, or deny plainly, Whether Chriſt doth enlighten people within, yea or nay? and to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and the light within; for until thou haſt done that, all thy Work is but confuſion; which if thou refuſe, let thy mouth be for ever ſtopped, as a mouth full of iniquity and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs.</p>
            <closer>Let all fleſh be ſilent.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>The Spirits Teſtimony to the true Light which every man that cometh into the world is enlightened with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Lord God of Life and Power hath in this his day made manifeſt to his Saints that which the World cannot believe, who have eyes, and ſee not; ears, and hear not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they underſtand with their hearts the things that God hath prepared for them that love him, but God hath revealed them unto his Babes whom he hath gathered out of the World,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174621:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>and hath opened their eye to ſee, and their ear to hear, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them a heart to perceive the things that belong to their peace, which confounds all the wiſe men of the World, who are ſearching into the things of God in their fallen Wiſdom, in which they can neither ſee nor perceive the myſterie of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Goſpel of Chriſt, and therefore they take counſel toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt it, and againſt the Lord and his annointed, crying Hereſie and Deluſion, Deceivers, Antichriſts, falſe Prophets are now come, beware of them that you be not deceived with them who talk of a Light within people to guide them by: And this is the cry both of Prieſts and Profeſſors at this day; and though they be at enmity in many things, and oppoſe one another, yet do they all join together, and take counſel to ſmite the upright, and make war with the Lamb; therefore in the movings of the Lord it is laid upon me to bear forth my Teſtimony for the Truths ſake, that none might abide in darkneſs, and be deceived by the Serpents ſubtilty, but that all might be turned from the darkneſs to the light, where pardoning mercy is felt and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, and in love to all in whom the living Witneſs is raiſed, that you may not be ſoon ſhaken, nor your deſires after the Truth be cooled, nor the pure be quenched, but that all who are breathing after God, may follow on to know him; for as the Day-ſpring from on high doth viſite you, all Clouds will va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away, and you will come to ſee above them; and ſo in the light of Chriſt waiting, you will come to ſee things that differ, and diſcern the precious from the vile, and ſo come to know what is of man, and what is of God; therefore believe not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpirit, but try the ſpirits whether they be of God, becauſe many falſe Prophets are in the World, who are covered with ſheeps clothing; therefore try them inwardly; the light makes them manifeſt, and the Wolfe is ſeen within; therefore try all things in the Light, and hold faſt that which is good; for theſe are perilous dayes, men are lovers of themſelves, covetous, proud boaſters, curſed ſpeakers, lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God; who have a ſhew of godlineſs, but deny the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer thereof, from ſuch turn away, for they reſiſt the truth, and are men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the faith; but now are they made manifeſt in the light, and their madneſs ſhall proceed no further; for the day hath declared them, and wolves
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174621:8"/>they do appear to be, their work is tryed of what ſort it is, and their foundation proves ſandy, and their building hey and ſtubble: Therefore be not toſſed up and down with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very wind of Doctrine, for form without power will not ſave you; nor can the Letter without the life give you peace; therefore let no man deceive you with vain Words, in cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Kingdom of God without you, as if it came with obſervations, but every one wait to know the Kingdom of God within you; for Chriſt preached it there, which every one is to look unto, from whence all good cometh, and the Lords love is freely opened, and his good and perfect gift is given, a meaſure to every one, by which they are enlighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made to know good from evil; for God ſo loved the World, that he gave his onely begotten Son who is the light of the World, and lighteth every man that cometh into the World, that all men through him might believe; and this wil be the condemnation of all that hate it, who are in the evil deeds, and will not come to the light leaſt their deeds ſhould be reproved; [mark] the evil deeds are made manifeſt by the light in the conſcience of a natural man, ſo that he ſees his deeds to be evil; but he hates the reproof of the light, and loves darkneſs rather, becauſe his deeds are evil. And this is the Lords tender mercy to all people, That he hath not left himſelf without a Witneſs in the conſcience of all the Sons and Daughters of men, which makes manifeſt their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil deeds, and teſtifieth againſt them, and calls them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; ſo will the Lord be clear when he judgeth, who would not the death of him that dyeth. Therefore all people conſider if ſuch a Witneſs you have not in your conſciences which teſtifieth againſt all your ungodlineſs, and ſearcheth you in ſecret, from which nothing can be hid; for it makes manifeſt the motions of ſin in you, and a motion is in the heart, then is it not within you? And is not that within you at all times, and in all places, which makes the motion of ſin manifeſt, and reproves you in your conſciences when you are in the tranſgreſſion, either by thought, word or deed? I am made to ſpeak plainly to manifeſt truth to the loweſt capacity, that all moderate ſpirits may conſider if that be not within them which doth ſecretly reprove them for ſin
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174621:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>and evil, which is Chriſt Jeſus the Light of the World, which the Serpentine Wiſdom calls Natures darkneſs, and would draw away peoples minds from it becauſe it doth diſcover his Kingdom, and his Works are deſtroyed by it; for this end was the Son of God made manifeſt, That he might deſtroy the Works of the Devil; and herein is Gods love tendered to all people, who hath enlightened all, and by his ſpirit ſtrives with them in this day of his patience, that his goodneſs might lead to repentance, and that his tender mercy might not be ſhut up in diſpleaſure; and thus doth he wait to be gracious, and makes manifeſt his love to ſinners, in that he takes them not away in their ſin, and in his ſore diſpleaſure, but gives them ſeveral viſitations by reprovings and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincements in their own conſciences for ſin and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that they might turn unto him, and feel his love o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened as a Fountain of living mercies: And this I am mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Lord to bear my teſtimony to, and there is that in all your conſciences that anſwers to the truth of it, unto which I am made manifeſt, which is the Witneſs of God in you all, and reproves you all who are in your ſins, for your iniquities; therefore I am made to exhort you all in the fear of the Lord God, to turn to the light which Chriſt hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened you withall, and obey it when it reproves you, and follow it when it leads you, and goes before you, ſo ſhall you not abide in darkneſs, but your feet ſhall be guided into the way of peace, which leadeth to eternal life; and though the World and formal profeſſors be crying Hereſie and Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet whoſoever waiteth in the light, ſhall feel food mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to ſatisfie the hungry, and ſtrength renewed to follow the Lord without wearineſs, and walk in his Way without faintneſs: And this is the eternal truth of the Lord God which I am made to bear forth my teſtimony to, as I know it in the Lord; and he that can receive it, let him.</p>
            <p>And now my dear Friends in the everlaſting truth of God, I feel my heart enlarged towards you, even to ſtir up your minds to the Lord God, that you may all keep ſtayed in the Light in which you are preſerved in perfect peace, though the ſeas roar, and the Waters thereof ſwell, and the Waves beat in the ſtormy tempeſt, you are at reſt in your deſired
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174621:9"/>Haven, there kept by the power of the lord God; &amp; though many Clouds ariſe to overſpread and darken your glorious day, ſo as to make your Sun ſet in a Cloud, yet in the light of Gods countenance do you walk as children of the Day, compaſſed about with his living mercies; therefore all keep faithful to the Lord God, in whoſe power you are all preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and watch in the light againſt your Enemy, for he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as ſubtilly within as he doth without, and labours to draw your minds into earthly things, but abide you in your Fathers Houſe, where the Bread is ſure, and the Water that faileth not; wait to feel the love of God ſhed abroad in your hearts, and in that love, love one another, and be tender-hearted one towards another; let all things be done in the pure Wiſdom of God, that he may have the praiſe in it; keep your ſelves unſpotted from the World, that your garments may be kept pure, and no ſtain may be upon them, having pure righteouſneſs for your robes; Watch over one another in the meek ſpirit, and be not raſh to judge, but ready to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh, that in love and unity all may grow in the meaſure of God, and feel his encreaſe. So all feed upon that Bread which comes down from Heaven, and drink of that Water which is in the living Fountain, that you may feed upon that which is eternal, whilſt the Serpent feeds upon the duſt. So in the light all dwell, that your hearts and minds may be kept clean and pure to the living God, that he may delight to dwell amongſt you, and walk in you, and have dominion, and reign, whoſe right it is, and no Weapon formed againſt you ſhall proſper: Therefore in nothing fear your adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which is to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of ſalvation, and that of God.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>The End.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
